Rocky Mountain Conference records, 1876-2010.
Congregational Library & Archives
Rocky Mountain Conference records, 1876-2010.
RG5424
Congregational Library & Archives
3.37 Cubic Feet
(4 boxes)
The Colorado Congregational Conference was founded in the 19th century and functioned as the primary state-level Congregational organization within Colorado. Numerous ministerial associations formed within Colorado and included the Eastern Association, the Arkansas Valley Association, the Denver Association, the Northwestern Association, and the Western Colorado Association. During the 1960s, the Colorado Conference merged with state level conferences from Utah and Wyoming to form the Rocky Mountain Conference of the United Church of Christ. This collection contains records related to the Rocky Mountain Conference, its predecessor conferences, especially the Colorado Congregational Conference, related state Congregational conferences, and regional associations within Colorado. The majority of records are meeting minutes for conferences and associations, programs for conference and association activities, financial records, correspondence and communications, and legal records.
Colorado Congregational Conference
United Church of Christ. Rocky Mountain Conference
Restrictions on Access
Access to this collection is unrestricted and open to the public.
Acquisition Information
Materials were donated to the Congregational Library & Archives by the Rocky Mountain Conference, August 2021; 2021-07, 2021-10.
Historical Note
The Colorado Congregational Conference was founded in the 19th century and functioned as the primary state-level Congregational organization within Colorado. The Colorado Congregational Conference also worked closely with the Board of Home Missions and the Extension Board to support and supply the churches within Colorado. Numerous ministerial associations formed within Colorado and included the Eastern Association, the Arkansas Valley Association, the Denver Association, the Northwestern Association, and the Western Colorado Association. The Colorado Conference also included numerous German Background Congregational churches. During the 1960s, the Colorado Conference merged with state level conferences from Utah and Wyoming to form the Rocky Mountain Conference of the United Church of Christ. The Rocky Mountain Conference continues today and has its headquarters in Denver. Under the Rocky Mountain Conference are modern day equivalents to the associations that existed in the past: the Metro Denver Association, the Platte Valley Association, the Western Colorado Association, the Southeast Association, and the Intermountain Association.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains records related to the Rocky Mountain Conference, its predecessor conferences, especially the Colorado Congregational Conference, related state Congregational conferences, and regional associations within Colorado. The records document the proceedings of these conferences and associations. The majority of records are meeting minutes for conferences and associations, programs for conference and association activities, financial records, correspondence and communications, and legal records. The collection contains records specifically related to the German Congregational churches within Colorado. The collection also contains a scrapbook documenting the local activities of the women's fellowship of the Rocky Mountain Conference.
Arrangement
Materials within this collection have been arranged into the three series listed below. Materials within the Colorado Congregational Conference records have been further organized into three subseries. Within each series, materials have generally been organized into chronological order. Directly related materials have been arranged together. Original order has largely been maintained for materials within each folder; as a result, contents within folders are rarely in chronological order.
Series 1: Colorado Congregational Conference records, 1877-2010
Subseries 1: Colorado State Conference records, 1877-1967
Subseries 2: Regional association records, 1901-1962
Subseries 3: German Congregational records, 1908-2010
Series 2: Other state conferences and associations, 1892-1983
Series 3: Rocky Mountain Conference records, 1969-2000
Clergy conferences.; Scrapbooks.; Colorado Congregational Conference; United Church of Christ. Rocky Mountain Conference
- Colorado Congregational Conference records, 1876 2010; 1876-2010; 8 Volumes; 45 Folders
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains records related to the Colorado Congregational Conference as well as the regional Associations that worked under the state Conference. The series also contains records specifically related to the German Background churches which were a part of the Colorado Congregational Conference. The collection contains meeting minutes, reports, correspondence, and programs.
  - Colorado State Conference records, 1876 1967; 1876-1967; 3 Volumes; 27 Folders
    This subseries contains records related to the Colorado Congregational Conference, and some other state-level Congregational records for the state of Colorado. This subseries contains meeting minutes, reports, board of directors' records, financial records, legal records, especially land deeds, records from the Colorado Home Missionary Society, records from the Extension Board, and communications with some churches.
    - Colorado Congregational Conference programs, 1876 1958; 1876-1958 (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - Colorado Congregational Association meeting clipping, 1877 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Colorado leagal records, 1883 1963; 1883-1963 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Colorado legal records, 1893-1919 (Folder 6)
    - Colorado Congregational Association Board of Directors records, 1895 1917; 1895-1917 (Box 2, Volume 1)
    - Colorado Congregational Association annual meeting minutes, 1901 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Colorado Home Missionary Society records, 1905 1913; 1905-1913 (Box 2, Volume 3)
    - Third Church, Denver, communications and clippings, 1911 1942; 1911, 1936-1942 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Colorado Conference State Board minutes, 1913 1927; 1913-1927 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Extension Board schedules for work, 1919 1930; 1919-1930 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Second Church, Denver, communications and clippings, 1926 1955; 1926-1955 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Colorado Congregational Conference meeting minutes, 1926 1928; 1926-1928 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Colorado Congregational Conference meeting minutes, 1928 1931; 1928-1931 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Colorado Congregational Conference meeting minutes, 1931 1933; 1931-1933 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Colorado Congregational Conference meeting minutes, 1933 1936; 1933-1936 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Colorado Congregational Conference meeting minutes, 1936 1938; 1936-1938 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Colorado Congregational Conference meeting minutes, 1938 1940; 1938-1940 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Extension Board applications for aid, 1927 1941; 1927-1941 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - History committee records, 1931 1965; 1931-1965 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Colorado State Conference reports, 1933 1938; 1933-1938 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Synodical record book, 1937 1963; 1937-1963 (Box 4, Volume 3)
    - Colorado Congregational Conference records, 1940 1947; 1940-1947 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Colorado Conference board of directors minutes, 1941 1965; 1941-1965 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - McCoy Community Church communications, 1942 1945; 1942-1945 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Colorado Congregational Conference reports, 1943 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Colorado Congregational Conference annual report, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Colorado Congregational Conference meeting minutes, 1946 1955; 1946-1955 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Colorado Congregational Conference treasurer's reports, 1947 1952; 1947-1952 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Commission on the Ministry minutes, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Colorado Conference annual reports, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Regional association records, 1901 1962; 1901-1962; 2 Volumes; 14 Folders
    This subseries contains records from the regional associations that functioned under the Colorado Congregational Conference. The associations represented in this subseries include the Arkansas Valley Association, Denver Association, Eastern Association, Northwestern Association, and Western Association. The records largely contain meeting minutes, programs, reports, and a significant collection of correspondence from the Denver Association.
    - Eastern Association records, 1901 1959; 1901-1959 (Box 1, Volume 1)
      Separated Materials
      Loose materials found within this volume were removed and placed into the folder titled "Northwestern Association records, 1933-1956" for preservation purposes.
    - Arkansas Valley Association programs, 1910 1927; 1910-1927 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Denver Association of Congregational Churches and Ministers records, 1912 1940; 1912-1940 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Arkansas Valley Association records, 1913 1943; 1913-1943 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Arkansas Valley Association records, 1944 1961; 1944-1961 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Colorado Western Association of Congregational Ministers and Churches records, 1924 1951; 1924-1951 (Box 2, Volume 4)
    - Denver association records, 1924 1954; 1924-1954 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Denver Association annual meeting programs, 1926 1938; 1926-1939 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Northwestern Association programs, 1927 1932; 1927-1932 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Northwestern Association records, 1933 1956; 1933-1956 (Box 1, Folder 11)
      Materials within this folder were removed from the volume titled "Eastern Association records, 1901-1959" for preservation purposes.
    - Western Colorado Association records: Union Congregational Church on Montrose, 1946 1950; 1946, 1950 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Denver Association correspondence: miscellaneous, 1946 1948; 1946-1948 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Denver Association correspondence: A-C, 1949 1955; 1949-1955 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Denver Association correspondence: D-M, 1946 1953; 1946-1953 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Denver Association correspondence: N-W, 1946 1953; 1946-1953 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Denver Association correspondence, 1955 1962; 1955-1962 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - German Congregational records, 1908 2010; 1908-2010; 3 Volumes; 4 Folders
    This subseries contains records specifically related to the German Background churches which were a part of the Colorado Congregational Conference. The subseries also contains communications with the Zion German Church in Montrose, Colorado, as well as records related to mission work with the German background churches.
    - Colorado Congregational Church (German background) records, 1908 1930; 1908-1930 (Box 2, Volume 2)
    - Zion German Church, Montrose, communications, 1929 1940; 1929-1940 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Colorado German Congregational Conference records, 1931 1952; 1931-1952 (Box 1, Volume 2)
    - Northeastern association of the Colorado Conference annual reports, 1952 1966; 1952-1966 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Northeastern Association financial records, 1952 2010; 1952-2010 (Box 4, Volume 2)
    - Colorado Conference German mission work, 1957 1962; 1957-1962 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Colorado Congregational Conference (German Background Churches) minutes, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 21)
- Other state conferences and associations, 1892 1983; 1892-1983; 1 Volume; 10 Folders
  This series contains records of Congregational conferences and associations from Idaho, Oregon, Utah, and Wyoming. The Rocky Mountain Conference of the UCC today includes Colorado, Utah, Wyoming. This series includes legal records, especially land deeds, financial records, records of conference and association meetings, constitutions, and programs.
  - Oregon legal records, 1892 1912; 1892-1912 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Utah legal records, 1909 1956; 1909-1914, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Idaho legal records, 1912 1934; 1912-1934 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Wyoming Conference constitution and incorporation, 1944 1956; 1944, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Wyoming Conference programs, 1945 1983; 1945-1983 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Idaho subsidary account book, 1946 1947; 1946-1947 (Box 1, Volume 3)
  - Rocky Mountain Synod minutes, 1946 1959; 1946-1959 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Idaho and Utah Conference financial records, 1947 1952; 1947-1952 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Intermountain Conference records, 1953 1974; 1953-1974 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Idaho Conference constitution, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Rocky Mountain Synod program, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 25)
- Rocky Mountain Conference records, 1969 2000; 1969-2000; 1 Folder; 1 Volume; 1 Object
  This series contains records related to the Rocky Mountain Conference. The series includes one volume of financial records, a scrapbook documenting the local activities, at the church level, of the Women's Fellowship of the Rocky Mountain Conference, and a gavel related to the Women's Fellowship.
  - Financial records, 1969 1983; 1969-1983 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Women's Fellowship scrapbook, 1975 2000; 1975-2000 (Box 4, Volume 1)
  - Women's Fellowship gavel, undated (Box 4, Object 1)